Hey everyone, and thanks for jumping
back into the equity verse. Today we're
going to talk about the S&P 500 as it
has once again made new all-time highs.
If you guys like the content, make sure
you subscribe to the channel, give the
video a thumbs up, and check out the
sale on ITC Premium at into the
cryptoverse.com.
As a reminder, we do have the conference
in Miami coming up in just a few months
now. So, make sure you guys uh get your
ticket. We've got a lot of great
speakers coming and I would love to see
you guys at the conference. Do know that
in the lowest tier it currently includes
the party that we'll have Saturday
night, but we are running out of spaces
for that. So that will only be included
in the higher tiers here in just a few
weeks. But if you sign up before we make
that change, you'll still be able uh to
go even in that lower tier. Let's go
ahead and jump in. So the S&P
is now at 7750. So, this is still very
much in line with how a lot of these
midterm years play out. In fact, one of
the things that we've talked about a lot
is how we would likely see new all-time
highs by the S&P going into sort of the
August time frame that even could extend
into September. And so, what we what we
should realize is how has it played out
in prior midterm years? When did we
actually start to see corrections? Now,
as a reminder, and I say this basically
in every video I do on stocks, I
buy index funds essentially monthly, and
I don't concern myself too much with
exactly where we are because it's really
hard to time the market. Even though,
you know, a lot of these corrections
were during periods of weakness, they
should in generally in general be used
to figure out when to buy rather than
when to sell in my opinion. But in this
case, I want to talk about kind of where
we are right now and are things aligning
in the same way they have in prior
midterm years. So, right now it's August
4th. The S&P is making new all-time
highs. Once again, that is sort of the
the base case that the stock market is
is it heading to new all-time highs. But
let's go take a look at when we got
these corrections in prior midterm years
and see, you know, if it if it might
line up once again. So, if you go back
to 2014, for instance, you'll see that
the S&P got a correction um in in about
what September. It started September
about midepptember
of 2014. It was about a 10% drop about a
10% drop. Now, if you look at the day
in which the top occurred, right, if we
want to really nail down the day, and
again, we shouldn't expect it to happen
on the same day either way, but it
started on September 19th. September
19th. In 2018,
when did the correction start?
It started in September,
but in this case, September 21st
with a lower high on October 3rd. But it
started technically
September 21st. So you have September
21st
in 2018.
And in 2014,
if you go look at um uh 2014, you have
September 19th. So
mid to late September, right? So you
have
September 19th, September 21st. Now in
2022, it was different. In 2022, we were
actually in a bare market and the top
ended up occurring on August 16th,
right? You can see that. And then we had
a lower high on September 12th and then
we ended up bottoming out in in about
mid October. So that in that case it was
actually mid August. So August 16th. So
you have three midterm years.
Right? You have three midterm years. And
in all three cases, the stock market had
about a 10 to 20% drop. Right? In 2014,
it was 10%, in 2018, it was 20%. And in
2022, it was in fact around 20%.
So, where we are right now, the S&P is
putting in new highs. Okay. Well, the
only time it wasn't really putting in
new highs at this point in the midterm
year was in the 2022 bare market when it
was going up, but it wasn't putting in
new highs because we were actually in a
bare market, right? Whereas the S&P in
2026 has been in a bull market. In 2018,
you can see the S&P was pushing to new
highs throughout all of August and even
going into September. If you look at
2014 again, you can see that it was
pushing to new all-time highs uh in in
August and September. So, what you're
seeing happen right now in the stock
market is is actually really similar to
what we've seen previously happen in the
stock market in midterm years. And this
is why when we talked about this phase
up here, right? When we looked at this
phase up here,
we said that we could very easily see
new highs before the correction occurs.
And the reason we said that is because
the correction normally doesn't start
until August or September. If we were
already in the correction in late July,
then the high would have actually been
in early June, that would have been very
different than what we've actually seen
in prior midterm years in recent
history. So, my argument here is that
the S&P again is breaking out. um could
stay bullish for a number of weeks, but
that come later August or even more
likely September,
I think the tides could shift. Now,
what is interesting about 2014 and 2018
is that the correction started on
September 19th and September 21st.
Coincidentally,
or maybe not coincidentally, the next
Fed meeting is September 16th.
And if you look at the probabilities
right now, the probability is about a
coin flip or so, right? It's about a
coin flip. You're looking at about a 57%
chance of a rate hike, a 43% chance that
they do absolutely nothing. And
what I sort of tend to think right now
is that the way this could play out like
it has played out in the last three
midterm years would be to get a
correction starting around the time of
the next Fed meeting again which is
about five or six weeks away about 6
weeks away. And the reason I say that is
because there's an argument to be had
that if the Fed does raise rates at the
next meeting.
And remember, the first time they cut
rates in 2025 was in September. The
first time they cut rates in 2024 was in
September. So perhaps they will raise
rates in September. And a lot of people
have said, "Well, they're not going to
raise rates in September." And they
might not. Like I don't I don't know for
sure that they're going to, but I would
argue that September might be a better
month to do it than a week before
midterms. and waiting until December
might cause the bond vigilantes to just
absolutely revolt if they wait until
December. So
if we were to get a rate hike in
September, then you might see that
correction occur
just because people are worried. Not
because the economy is necessarily
crumbling, just because people are
worried that the easing cycle is over
and then we're going back into a a
hiking cycle.
If the Fed were not to raise rates in
September, then the argument would
simply be that the long end of the yield
curve is going to go higher. You're
likely going to have the 10-year yield
breaking out above 5%. It's already
heading in that direction now. Uh, you
know, if you look at the 10ear yield,
it's at 4.6%.
And my guess, and we've been talking
about this for a while, is that it will
likely head back up to where it was in
October of 2023. Note, the 30-year yield
has already made it there, right? The
30-year yield has already broken through
where it was in October 2023. So, I
think it's only a matter of time before
the 10-year yield uh gets there as well.
And I I think that's something important
to watch here over the next couple of
months. So, going back to the S&P, you
know, when we think about what is the
most likely outcome here,
I think in the short term, you're likely
going to see more or less the same
stuff. The S&P is has sort of broken
out. You're likely going to see this
bullishness continue would my guess
would be for at least a few more weeks.
Um, unless we're just going completely
faked out and sometime
potentially in October, but I would lean
towards September at this point.
sometime in September
getting that correction that then ushers
in what I would consider to be the
market cycle bottom for Bitcoin. Now,
when I talk about a correction in stocks
that will likely occur starting in
August or September, I'm saying it
starts then. I'm not saying it finishes
then. So, for instance, in 2018, it
would have been objectively true that
the stock market would have started
correcting in September because that's
when it topped. But would it have become
obvious to everyone by early October?
No. The correction did not finish until
December.
In 2014, if you said that the stock
market would start a correction around
September, would you have been right?
Yeah, you would have been. Because when
you look at at where the stock market
was on September 20 or sorry, September,
what was it? 19th. September 19th, it
was at all-time highs, but it in it
didn't bottom out until about
mid-occtober. And in 2022, when the
stock market found a high in mid August,
the low wasn't set again until
midocctober. So the argument to be made
here in my opinion is that if the
correction occurs in the same way it did
in the last three midterm years, while
the correction would start more than
likely in September or potentially as
early as August, while it would start in
September, it probably wouldn't be over
in September. It could go into o it
could go into October. It could go into
November. And if it does what 2018 did,
it could even go into December.
If you look at the year-to- date ROI
of the stock market in 2026 and compare
that to 2014,
you can see that the the correction that
I'm talking about didn't occur until
like later on in September. You see
that? And if you compare it to 2018,
you can see the correction did not start
again until uh until September, but it
wasn't obvious to people until October.
And in 2022, it's going to look a little
bit different because we were in a bare
market, but you can see it didn't start
until about mid August. So, if you were
to average out
the last three midterm years, let's call
2022, 2018, 2014,
and look at where the S&P is, you can
see that we're actually a bit higher
than we normally are on average, but
that the window of weakness on average
doesn't really start until about that
mid August to September time frame. So,
we're seeing new new all-time highs
right now. Again, I don't ever sell my
index funds. Um, happy to see the stock
market go higher, but I would argue that
when we do get that drop, I think it
would probably just be another another
opportunity uh for those that that want
to get in. We've had plenty of them um
throughout the last several years and
and this would likely just be one more.
So, we'll see if that actually comes to
pass or not. I mean,
time is is kind of the uh the issue here
in the short term of like, you know, in
the short term S&Ps breaking out to new
highs, that could very well continue for
a number of weeks. Uh so, we're not
going to really get an answer out our
question until a couple of months from
now. And we'll either be looking back
and saying, "All right, well, the S&P
found a local top in August or
September, or it didn't." And my guess
is that it will. Um, but the thing I
would caution people to about trying to
time the markets too much is let's say
you get a 10% drop, right? And you're
waiting for that. There's always a
chance that the 10% drop is to a lower
is to a higher price than where you
could have just bought in the first
place. Okay? So, it's important to
remember that I'm I'm primarily using
the S&P in this case to try to
understand when Bitcoin's
theoretical market cycle bottom would in
fact be. And normally the market cycle
bottom for Bitcoin
occurs in the in the correction the
stock market that occurs in the back
half of the year. So in 2022, the stock
market had a correction early on, but it
wasn't until the second correction that
Bitcoin bottomed. In 2018, the stock
market had a big correction early on,
but it wasn't until the second
correction that Bitcoin bottomed. And in
2014,
the stock market had a small correction
um early on in the year, but it wasn't
until the the larger correction that
occurred later, which was to a higher
low, but a larger correction by
percentage. It wasn't until that
correction that Bitcoin actually
bottomed. And so the argument is that we
are simply repeating the last three
midterm years. We already have the
original correction in the beginning of
2026, right? Like you can see we have
it. So you have, if you were to label
these, you have one, one, one, your
first correction. And in each case, you
have a second correction that doesn't
really kick off until mid August at the
earliest or late September at the
latest. And so that's the argument that
this is going to play out probably in
the same way that it has in the last
three midterm years. And again, I'm just
sort of a big believer. And if it's not
broke, don't fix it. All right. Now, if
you look at the S&P, it has um you know,
basically it went sideways for a little
while, found support near the bull
market support band, and then went ahead
and moved up. Um I was actually looking
at this this this pattern. We've
actually seen something like this before
on the Bitcoin chart. Like if you look
at the Bitcoin chart, you can see
remember last year when Bitcoin, you
know, it came below here, consolidated,
went up, and then went sideways until
almost the bull market support band
caught up, and then it went up
and then eventually it came back down.
To me,
it looks a little familiar. Like I'm not
huge into fractals and whatnot because
they usually don't play out um in the
way that that many people think they
will. But if you were to simply overlay
the idea, right? If you were to overlay
the idea,
you can kind of see like, you know, what
it is I'm talking about, right? How you
you you get your your low,
right? like you get your low that forms
and it's hard to know exactly how to
line up, but you get your initial low
that forms, you rally on up, you go
sideways, you push up, and then
eventually you get a deeper correction.
And so that's the argument is that when
you get a deeper correction, likely
later this year that you're basically
checking back in with this longer term
trend line in the S&P 500. Now, I don't
know if I don't know if it's going to go
all the way back down to 6,000 or not,
but it's a possibility. And imagine if
it did. I mean, that would be a pretty
brutal correction. If it did, that would
very likely cause Bitcoin to lose that
support that it has at at 60K. Now, if
it doesn't, I could be wrong. I could be
wrong. If you look at Bitcoin in 2018,
remember, it held support at $6,000 for
the entire year. And it wasn't until the
second correction by the stock market
that that actually that actually took
Bitcoin down to those lows, right? So
the stock market didn't even go that
much lower than where it was at the
beginning of the year.
So if you look at the first correction
it had in 2018, the stock market only
went about 7 to 8% below that. But even
though the stock market only went 7 to
8% below that, Bitcoin
went about 48% below. Now if you look at
Bitcoin this year, this is certainly a
less volatile version of 2018, right?
Right? If you look at the year-to- date
ROI of Bitcoin
in 2026 and look at it compared to 2018,
you can see it kind of the moves kind of
line up, but we haven't had, you know,
that larger correction in the S&P yet
that normally occurs, not even starting
until August or September. Remember, I'm
not saying the correction in stocks ends
in September. I'm saying it could not
start until September. And if you look
at two of the last three stock market
corrections that occurred in midterm
years, they didn't start until September
19th or 20th, which is around when the
next Fed funds meeting is. So you could
argue if they raise rates, people might
panic, even though there's probably
nothing to panic about. And if they
don't raise rates, people might panic if
inflation continues to print levels that
are are somewhat concerning. And I think
the the thing to watch here is just the
bond market because the bond market is
is where a lot of this stuff is going to
play out. Does the 30-year yield
continue to go higher? Does the 10-year
yield continue to go higher? If yields
continue to go higher for the next, say,
six weeks or so, then it certainly would
set up the the only narrative you would
need to get sort of a secondary
correction in stocks in the back half of
the year, the back half of of of the
midterm year. So, that is is my view
here on the stock market. And also too,
I mean, with the dollar, I I think the
dollar, while it is down recently, I
think it's just simply printing a higher
low. and is likely going to continue to
head back up. One interesting thing
about the dollar is if you look at the
the presidential return path, so
basically the the way in which certain
assets perform during various
presidencies. If you look at first of
all, if you look at the S&P in 2026,
like if you look at the current S&P
compared to Donald Trump's first term or
his first term, we're basically at the
same valuation we were back then. You
know, like things are really not that
different. What's also interesting is if
you look at the dollar, the Dixie DXY in
Trump's current term compared to 2017
2018, um you can see it's also tracking
basically the same. And if it continues
to track, then the dollar should get
another move higher a little bit later
on in the year, which might actually be
that headwind that causes these risk
assets to show weakness one more time a
little bit later on in the midterm year.
So again, my encouragement, again, not
financial advice, but my encouragement,
generally speaking, is to use this stuff
to figure out kind of good opportunities
to get in, not try to time things on
when to sell or anything like that. I my
strategy for the last five or six years,
as I've mentioned, is to just buy low
expense ratio index funds and hope for
the best. And I mean, it works out
decently well. It it works out better
than a lot of people that just stock
pick constantly. Um, and I do
occasionally buy some stocks, but or
individual stocks, but index funds with
low expense ratios are, in fact, my
opinion, they've been a good way to go
for for a long time. So, those are my
views about the stock market. We're
currently at all-time highs. Usually,
all-time highs just lead to new all-time
highs, which I know kind of sounds
weird, but it's true, right? When the
stock market's putting in new all-time
highs, it tends to continue to want to
for a little while before that before
that changes course. And if history is
any indication, we won't likely see that
change course until at least mid August
at the earliest, but maybe not until say
midepptember if it's going to play out
like it did in 2014 and or 2018. If you
guys like the content, make sure you
subscribe to the channel, give the video
a thumbs up, and I'd love to see you
guys at the Investing Through the Cycles
conference taking place in Miami this
November. Make sure you guys get your
ticket. Links in the description below
or the pinned comment. I'll see you guys
next time. Bye.